每一天 世界上令我们惊奇的动物都在消失
every day,natural wonders of our world disappear.
有些是慢慢死亡的
some slip away quietly,
没人注意
without notice,
没人宣告
without fanfare.
一只再也不能在野外飞翔的鹦鹉
a parrot that no longer flies in the wild,
地球上同类乌龟中的 最后一个幸存者
a turtle that is the last of his kind on earth,
自相残杀的幼兽
and babies that are killing each other
科学家正努力地 挽救这些动物
as scientists struggle to bring them back to life.
多姿多彩、魅力非凡的动物
colorful and charismatic,
这些受困的动物面临着 一个未知的未来
these embattled creatures face an uncertain future.
苏门答腊犀牛
man: the sumatran rhino is going to
在未来20年的生死存亡
live or die in the next 20 years,
归因于人类及其行为
because of humans and human actions.
如果人类让非凡的动物灭绝
and I think it would be reprehensible if humans
我认为这是应该受谴责的事情
allowed such a magnificent animal to go extinct.
如果我们不能成功地 繁殖这些动物
man: if we cannot succeed with breeding them,
那么它们就会灭绝
then these animals will be doomed,
因为它们都死掉了
because there are no more.
在实验室中圈养动物
but will protecting animals in captivity
并繁殖后代
and breeding generations in a lab
这样能阻止动物灭绝吗？
stem the extinction tide?
你不能把这些动物
man: you can't return something like
例如苏门答腊犀牛
a sumatran rhino
或者伊比利亚猞猁
or an iberian lynx
再放回旧环境中
to just any old environment.
它们真的需要回到 自己进化的环境中
it really needs to be returned to the environment that it evolved in.
我们不想动物都被囚禁在监笼
woman: we don't want them in jail --
我们要让动物回到野外
we want them out in the wild
自由奔跑
and free-roaming.
这些是在死亡边缘的幸存者
these are the survivors on the edge,
地球上极度濒危的动物
the most endangered species on the planet,
世界上最孤独的动物
the loneliest animals in the world.
最孤独的动物
==================================== 记录片之家倾情奉献 http://www.jlpzj.com/ 本字幕仅供学习交流 严禁用于商业用途 ==================================== 翻译/时间轴/校对:laser
自然
想象一下 在早上
imagine it's morning.
你醒过来 孤单一人
you wake up and you're totally alone.
你有90岁了
you're 90 years old,
你是同类中的 最后一个幸存者
and you're the last of your kind on earth.
在加拉帕哥斯群岛
in the galapagos islands,
一只大乌龟就是这样 孤独地生活着
one giant tortoise lives this extreme solitary existence.
看看这个地球上 最孤独的动物吧
meet the loneliest animal in the world --
寂寞乔治
lonesome george.
乔治来自平塔岛
george is from pinta island,
加拉帕哥斯群岛中的独立小岛
an isolated outpost of the galapagos.
几个世纪以来
for centuries,
水手和海盗为了获取龟肉
sailors and pirates plundered his island
洗劫乔治的小岛
for tortoise meat
直到他们认为 再也没有乌龟了
until they thought there were no more.
37年前
37 years ago,
研究者找到最后一个幸存者
researchers found there was one last survivor --
乔治
george.
我们认为90岁很长寿
90 years is a long life for us,
但是乌龟在90岁 处于中年期
but it's mere middle age for a tortoise.
乔治最终死掉的时候
when george does finally die,
几百万年的进化历程 也到了尽头
millions of years of evolution will come to an end.
然而 从某种意义上来说
yet,in one way,
寂寞乔治一点也不孤独
lonesome george is not alone at all.
科学家警告说 每一天
scientists warn that up to 100 species a day
有近100种动物濒临灭绝
are pushed into extinction.
现在 有几个幸存者的少数物种
but now,for a few species with a handful of survivors,
希望的曙光来了
there could be a glimmer of hope.
[ 相机快门滴答声 ]
[ camera shutter clicking ]
中国湖南省
hunan province,china.
南部城市长沙
in the southern city of changsha,
摄影师云集当地动物园
the paparazzi converge on the local zoo.
摄影师正在追逐拍摄 一个家乡明星
they're angling for a glimpse of a hometown star.
中国最稀有的珍宝之一
one of china's rarest treasures.
她是一只杨子大软壳乌龟
she's a yangtze giant soft-shelled turtle,
斑鳖
rafetus swinhoei,
她要开始一趟旅程
and she's about to embark on a journey
这关乎斑鳖物种的命运
that will determine the fate of her species.
斑鳖曾经活跃在长江流域
rafetus turtles once flourished throughout the yangtze river valley.
但是中国的城市化建设 破坏了斑鳖的栖息地
but china's meteoric modernization destroyed their habitat
过度捕猎令最后一个受害者 都死掉了
and overhunting killed off the last survivors.
100多年来 只有一只斑鳖
for over half a century,one rafetus turtle
孤独地生活在长沙动物园
lived with little fanfare at the changsha zoo.
两年前
then,two years ago,
动物园发现了 这个引入注目的动物
the zoo discovered they had something extraordinary --
最后一个地球上 已知的雌性斑鳖
the last known female on the planet.
现在她有80岁了
now over 80 years old,
生活在防护玻璃后面
she's kept behind protective glass,
24小时受到监控
under 24-hour surveillance.
不可避免的是
it seems inevitable that rafetus turtles
斑鳖是将要消失的 又一个中国自然奇观
will be the next of china's natural wonders to disappear...
除非这个国际生物学家小组 能够挽回这种局面
unless this team of international biologists cacan turn their story around.
领队Gerald kuchling博士
led by dr.gerald kuchling
来自拯救龟类联盟
from the turtle survival alliance,
这个小组来这里见证 一个历史性的联姻日子
the team has come to oversee a historic blind date,
因为在600里外的苏州
for in suzhou,600 hundred miles away,
生活着她的同类
lives her counterpart --
中国最后一个 已知的雄性斑鳖
the last known male rafetus in china.
坦白说 我们要抓住这个最后的机会
man: it's basically the last chance we have
来挽救这种特殊的动物
to keep this particular species on our planet.
如果我们不能成功地繁殖斑鳖
if we cannot succeed with breeding them,
那么斑鳖就完蛋了
then these animals will be doomed
因为再也没有斑鳖了
because there are no more.
一般来说
man: so,normally,
斑鳖每年产卵两次 每次两个
they lay eggs two -- twice in one year.
每年夏天
abraham: every summer,
雌性斑鳖产两次卵
the female lays two clutches of eggs.
一般卵的大小都一样吗？
man: are they usually all about the same size?
但是 缺了雄性斑鳖
abraham: but without a mate,
卵无法受精
they remain unfertilized.
今年 小组有两个星期的时间
this year,the team has a two-week window
来促成斑鳖交配
to encourage her to mate with the male
因此她能注入卵子
so he can inject her yearly eggs
为斑鳖的未来带来希望
with hope for the future of their kind.
雌性斑鳖是珍贵的货物
the female is precious cargo,
在旅途中 要优先考虑并确保她的安全
and first priority is to ensure her safety on the long journey.
Scott davis博士有多年的经验
dr.scott davis brings years of experience
来安置软壳乌龟
with handling soft-shelled turtles to the team.
现在是春天
davis: right now it's spring,
雄性和雌性斑鳖
and the male and the female that we're working with
刚好度过冬眠
have just come out of hibernation,
这是介绍他们认识的最佳时机
and so it's the perfect time to introduce them
希望他们能自然交配
and hopefully they'll mate naturally
她能产下可受精的卵
and she'll lay fertile eggs.
她知道我们在谈论她
she knew we were talking about her.
呀 是的 她的私事
ah,yeah,yeah.her private business.
她想说再见
she wants to say goodbye.
计划很简单
abraham: the set-up is simple,
但是风险很大
but the plan is fraught with risks.
两个斑鳖都差不多100岁了
both animals are nearly 100 years old,
在他们的长久独处生活中
and in their lg,solitary lives,
有可能他们从没遇到过异性
it's possible they've never met a member of the opposite sex.
上一次雄性斑鳖遇到同类时
the last time the male encountered another turtle,
他杀了别人
he killed him.
雌性斑鳖的安全 握在科学家的手里
the safety of the female is in the scientists' hands.
好的
okay.
放开她
leave it.
噢 她滑下来的吗？
oh,she slipped down?
Kuchling博士正在 测试一个快速超声仪
abraham: dr.kuchling oversees a quick ultrasound
以确保她是否准备交配
to make sure she's ready for a mate.
好消息
and then,good news.
9个卵子
雌性斑鳖有卵
the female is full of eggs that should be
大约8个星期后 就能产下来了
ready to lay in about eight weeks.
她的状态很好
she is in perfect condition.
放到这里 盖住她
davis: set her up here with her head covered.
现在要抓紧赶路
abraham: it's now urgent to get on the road
尽可能快
as quickly as possible.
她滑下来了
man: she's slipping...
安置好她
davis: there she goes.
我们办好了 噢 啊
we got her.oh,whoa,mama,
噢 放松点
whoa,whoa,easy,easy,easy.
小组还要赶路17个小时
abraham: ahead,the team faces a 17 hour drive,
路途遥远
and it will be a long one.
递水给我
davis: give me that water!
水来了！
water!
不要 甜心 不要！
no,sweetheart,no!
不要！
don't!
小组要保持乌龟潮湿
abraham: the team has to wrestle with keeping the turtle wet
防止乌龟受伤
and preventing her from hurting herself.
她不开心
she is unhappy.
谢天谢地 几个小时后
thankfully,after a few hours,
她在路途上放弃挣扎了
she gives in to the journey.
进展很顺利
davis: it's going very well.
她舒服地安顿下来了
we've got her comfortably settled
安详地睡觉
and she's peacefully asleep.
我想她一路上都会睡觉
I think she'll sleep all the way there.
让这些最后的古老动物配对的尝试
abraham: the attempt to pair the last of these ancient turtles
让我们认识到 我们对这些动物的了解是少之又少
confronts us with how little we know about our fellow creatures.
现在 在我们发现这些动物的生存状况之前 有很多要灭亡了
now,many are poised to disapar before we discover why they were here.
我想我们要竭尽全力
man: I think we have to put effort into saving
力所能及地挽救这些动物
whatever we can save,and even if this is
即使濒危动物被圈养
apparently doomed species being maintained in captivity
他们很快被放回野外的 希望不大
with no immediate prospect for going back to the wild,
我们必须这样做
we have to do this.
人类也是动物 生存也要依靠其他动物
we as living creatures ourselves depend on other forms of life for our own survival
生态系统也需要这些动物
and for the ecological processes that they generate.
只有还有幸存的个体动物
as long as there's some individuals left of a species,
我们就不应该放弃
we should not give up.
我们应该竭尽所能
we should make every effort possible
挽救这些濒临灭绝的动物
to bring them back from the brink.
虽然繁殖爬行动物相对容易
abraham: but breeding reptiles is relatively easy.
雄性和雌性能在适当的季节交配
a male and female in the right season should mate.
性别的社交性很复杂
with other species,the social side of sex reaches a complexity
我们才刚开始了解
we are just beginning to understand.
在印度尼西亚的苏门答腊岛南部
in southern sumatra,indonesia,
森林巡逻队忠于职守
a forest patrol unit reports for duty.
Way Kambas国家公园的 水陆警察分队
the squad polices the jungles and waterways of way kambas national park,
公园是海岸森林带
a sliver of coastal forest.
每天24小时
24 hours a day,
分队保护树木 防止伐木者砍伐
the unit safeguards the trees from loggers
解除偷猎者设置的陷阱
and dismantles the deadly traps set by poachers.
他们的目标是
their goal --
保护这些稀有动物
to protect an animal so rare,they only see it
他们一年才遇到这些动物两三次
two or three times a year --
苏门答腊犀牛
the sumatran rhinoceros.
苏门答腊犀牛是 已经灭绝的披毛犀的后代
sumatran rhinos are descendents of the extinct woolly rhino,
他们至今还保留了 祖先的蓬松皮毛
and they still bear their ancestor's shaggy coat.
他们是唯一一种用歌唱发声 来交流的犀牛
they're the only rhino species that communicates in song-like vocalizations --
鲸鱼和海豚也用这种方式交流
a trait they share with whales and dolphins.
在五种犀牛中 他们的体型最小
they're the smallest of the five rhino species
也最濒临灭绝
and also the most endangered.
过去20年来
in the last 20 years,poaching has slashed
偷猎者令他们的数降低了70%多
their population by more than 70%.
苏门答腊犀牛在过去也受到威胁
man: the sumatran rhino historically has been threatened
因为有人偷猎犀牛角
because of poaching for their horn.
这种犀牛角比非洲犀牛角还珍贵
this small horn is even more valuable than the african rhino horns.
每公斤2.5-3万美元
it sells for between $25,000 and $30,000 a kilogram.
现在 更大的威胁是 森林砍伐
today,an even bigger danger is deforestation.
过去5年来
in the last five years,
印度尼西亚的森林
indonesia's forests
每分钟就减少 相当于5个足球场的面积
have lost the equivalent of five football fields per minute.
现在 在剩下的森林里
now,fewer than 200 sumatran rhinos
只有不到200个犀牛挣扎在死亡线上
are hanging onto survival in what little remains.
Robin radcliffe博士的任务是
dr.robin radcliffe is on a mission
拯救全球的犀牛
to save the world's rhinos.
他一年来Way kambas公园两次
twice a year,he comes to way kambas
在苏门答腊犀牛保护区工作
to work at the sumatran rhino sanctuary.
好 结实的脚部
good,solid sole.
你很好 Rosa
you're okay,rosa.
好女孩
good girl.
他们是奇妙的动物
radcliffe: they're incredibly amazing creatures.
史前动物
they're prehistoric.
看看这片下部胸肉
look at these armor plates.
他们是非常原始的动物
these guys are very primitive --
过去四五千万年
in the past 40 to 50 million years,
他们都没有任何改变
they haven't changed at all.
保护区有250亩的森林
abraham: the sanctuary encloses 250 acres of protected forest
少数几个犀牛生活在不同的领地
where a handful of rhinos live in divided territories.
10年前
ten years ago,
他们发起了一个圈养繁殖计划
they launched a captive breeding program
来增加不断减少的野外犀牛数量
to bolster the dwindling wild population.
但是养殖这些原始动物 并不容易
but breeding these primeval creatures hasn't proved easy.
他们原始的求爱行为 依然是个谜
their wild courtship behavior remains a mystery,
保护区的雄性犀牛 越来越老了
and the one male at the sanctuary was aging
可能已经不能受精
and possibly infertile.
5年后
after five years,
保护区没有犀牛成功繁殖
the sanctuary had failed to produce a single baby rhino.
焦急的小组人员寻求突破
the anxious team needed a breakthrough,
重振这个计划
something to jump-start the program.
1万里外的辛辛那提动物园
then,10,000 miles away at the cincinnati zoo,
Andalas出生了
andalas was born.
Andalas是100多年来因圈养繁殖而出生的 首个苏门答腊犀牛
andalas was the first captive-born sumatran rhino in more than 100 years,
他花了6年时间在动物园长大
and he spent six years growing up at the zoo.
2007年 他回到了家乡 一次历史性的旅程
in 2007,he made a historic journey to his ancestral home.
旅途花了63个小时
man: the trip took about 63 hours.
他一直在板条箱里
he was in a crate the entire time.
他首先坐飞机 然后改乘卡车
he first traveled by airplane,then by truck,
接着乘船渡过Sunda海峡 来到苏门答腊岛
then by ferry across the sunda strait to sumatra,
然后再乘卡车到达保护区
then by truck again finally to the sanctuary.
虽然现在他还年轻 他将是未来的
even though he's young,he will be the future
苏门答腊犀牛保护区的 繁殖父亲 即公牛
breeding sire,or bull,here at the sumatran rhino sanctuary.
现在Andalas六岁了
abraham: now six years old,
正值青年
andalas is just reaching adolescence.
要让他发育成超级公牛 小组正在决定该做些什么
the team is trying to determine what he may need to develop into a top bull.
苏门答腊犀牛可能是 最难圈养繁殖的犀牛
radcliffe: sumatran rhinos are probably the most difficult rhinoceros species to breed in captivity.
在过去 部分原因是
part of it,historically,
我们不知道他们如何成长
was we just didn't know how they worked.
好孩子 Andalas.
good boy,andalas.
好了
over.
目前我们只希望他们健全正常
right now we just want to get normals.
鉴于苏门答腊犀牛的数量非常少
because sumatran rhinos are so rare,
我们甚至不知道 正常值是多少
we don't even know what normal values are.
好孩子 Aandalas.
good boy,andalas.
Andalas的首次候选的交配
abraham: andalas' first potential mate
是和年轻美丽的Rosa
is a young beauty named rosa.
[ Rosa发出歌唱呼唤 ]
[ rosa makes song-like call ]
Radcliffe及其同事正在研究Rosa
dr.radcliffe and his colleagues are studying rosa
找到她准备当妈妈的时间
to find out when she'll be ready for motherhood.
现在 结果令人鼓舞
and today,the results bring good news.
Rosa刚到这里的时候
radcliffe: when rosa first came here,
她的卵巢活动非常少
she had very little activity on her ovaries.
换句话说 我们没在超声波上看到小囊
in other words,we didn't see on the ultrasound,we didn't see these follicles.
这意味着她正在开始循环
this means that she's starting to cycle,
她很快有希望进行繁殖了
and hopefully she'll be able to breed soon.
这是个好兆头
this is a really good sign.
Andalas和Rosa是保护区的希望
abraham: andalas and rosa are the hope of the sanctuary.
但是即使他们孕育了孩子
but even if they achieve a baby,
显而易见 只有圈养繁殖
it's clear that captive breeding alone
并不能阻止犀牛灭绝
is not going to prevent their extinction.
我认为不能采用圈养繁殖 来挽救苏门答腊犀牛
radcliffe: I don't believe that the sumatran rhino can be saved in captivity.
支持这个计划的捐款人
clearly,the donors who support this place
希望看到一些犀牛后代 这是很重要的
want to see some offspring,and I think that's important,
但是这个工作的实质
but the bulk of the work has to be done
是要在野外挽救犀牛
in saving the animals in the wild,
保护公园 教育人民
protecting the national parks and educating people,
确保很好地实施法律
and making sure we have good law enforcement.
?
虽然让Andalas和Rosa繁殖后代 有很大压力
abraham: while the pressure is on andalas and rosa to produce some offspring,
保护区召集新一代的孩子
the sanctuary is reaching out to a new generation of children
这些孩子会保护这些奇妙的动物
who will protect and preserve these enigmatic animals.
[ 孩子发出笑声 ]
[ children laughing ]
苏门答腊犀牛 未来20年的生死存亡
radcliffe: the sumatran rhino is going to live or die
都取决于人类及其行为
in the next 20 years because of humans and human actions,
如果人类让非凡的动物灭绝
and I think it would be reprehensible
我认为这是应该受谴责的事情
if humans allowed such a magnificent animal to go extinct.
“苏门答腊犀牛是世界的遗产”
苏门答腊犀牛保护区
abraham: the sumatran rhino sanctuary
是在多个前线战斗
is fighting a battle on several fronts --
致力于圈养繁殖动物
pioneering efforts to breed the animals in captivity,
保护森林栖息地
but also defending their forest habitat
防止野生犀牛灭绝
and the last rhinos left in the wild.
和其它动物一样
with other species,
再也没有野生动物保护了
there are no wild animals left to protect.
在波斯湾的卡塔尔中心
secluded in the heart of the persian gulf nation of qatar,
沙漠隐藏着一片绿洲
the desert obscures an unlikely oasis.
濒危的非洲羚羊
endangered african antelopes,
它们和野生驴 还有沙漠猫科动物
wild asses,and sand cats
一起生活
live side by side.
中心还有不可能存在的
and in its center stands the impossible --
热带森林
a rain forest
坐落在灼热的沙漠中心
in the middle of the scorching desert.
这是由Sheikh saoud mohammed bin al thani建造的
built by sheikh saoud mohammed bin al thani,
Al Wabra野生动物保护中心
the al wabra wildlife preservation center shelters
有超过2000种稀有而极度濒危动物
over 2,000 rare and critically endangered animals.
在这离家7000里的地方
and here,7,000 miles from home,
一种巴西鸟获得了 生命的最后机会
a brazilian bird is getting a last chance at life --
斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉
the spix's macaw.
斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉一度在巴西北部
spix's macaws once thrived
荒芜、干燥的森林中繁衍
in the harsh,dry forest of northeastern brazil.
直至1995年
by 1995,
捕获鹦鹉作为宠物的交易
trapping for the exotic pet trade
以及森林的毁坏
and the destruction of the forest
使这种野生鸟类的数量下降
had reduced the wild bird's population
现在只剩下唯一一个顽强的鹦鹉了
to a single tenacious parrot.
2000年
then,in 2000,
最后一个野生鹦鹉死亡了
the last wild bird disappeared.
随着最后一只野生鹦鹉的死亡
man: the extinction of the spix's macaw
斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉灭绝
with the disappearance of that last bird,
真的令人深思
I think,was a really remarkable moment.
没有公众关注
it attracted almost no publicity,however -- despite the fact
虽然我们损失了地球上 无法替代的动物
that we'd lost an irreplaceable piece of life on earth,
几乎没有头条新闻
there were almost no headlines.
这个消息传给了Sheikh saoud博士
abraham: the news did reach sheikh saoud,
他在Al Wabra的小组养殖了 很多快绝种的鸟类
and his team at al wabra bought up many of the last birds in captivity.
这些鸟类的来源 远至瑞士
from as far away as switzerland
还有菲律宾
and the philippines,
这些鸟被带回 沙漠的独立笼子里
they've come to this isolated ark in the desert.
这个地方的主要目标
man: the special focus of this place
是增加极度濒危动物的数量
is to increase the number of highly endangered animals.
保护区的一些动物
and we have some animals here in this preservation
没有其他人圈养繁殖他们
nobody else have them in captivity.
我们试图增加这些极度濒危的动物的数量
we try to increase the number of these highly endangered animals,
例如斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉 希望某一天
like the spix's macaw,and hopefully one day
我们可以把这些动物放回大自然
we can bring them back to the nature,
或者 像斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉
or,in this case of the spix's macaw,
把他找回来 让他再次飞翔
to bring him back and let him fly again.
Ryan Watson的工作时间都花在稀有鸟类上
abraham: ryan watson has spent his lifeworking with rare birds,
5年前 这种最稀有的鹦鹉
and five years ago,the rarest of all
吸引他来到Al Wabra保护区
lured him to al wabra.
Al wabra保护区有 49只斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉
man: at al wabra,we have 49 spix's macaws
而全世界已登记的有77只
of the 77 in the international managed studbook.
所以这里的斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉 占了世界数量的大多数
so we have a very significant portion of the world population.
这里的工作非常重要
so the work we're doing here is very important in the attempts
争取某一天重新把它们放回野外
to one day re-establish the species in the wild
那才是真正属于它们的地方
where they truly belong.
不
no.
Al wabra极度偏僻
abraham: al wabra's extreme isolation
后勤服务面临很大的挑战
presents enormous logistical challenges --
包括维持一个训练良好的小组
from maintaining a well-trained staff
供应新鲜水、食物、药物
to supplying fresh water,food,and medicine
这里是最贫瘠的地方
in the most barren of landscapes.
我们有100种动物
we have 100 different species.
最小的重4公斤
my smallest patient is four grams
最大的重400公斤
and my biggest is 400 kilos.
面对100种动物
if you have 100 different animals,
你需要100种不同的食物
you need 100 different kind of food mixture.
许多食物来自欧洲
and we supply a lot of the food we need from europe,
每6个月用食物集装箱运一次
with food container which comes in every six months.
因此 我们就像在一座荒岛上
so,we are like on an island.
孤立的小岛也有一个好处
abraham: the isolation does have a benefit --
可以自然隔离
it creates a natural quarantine...
防止疾病传染进来
preventing the influx of disease
保护珍贵的动物
and protecting priceless creatures
他们是同类中的幸存者
that are among the last of their kind.
来吧!
come on!
这些笼子里的天蓝色鹦鹉
the sky-blue macaws in these cages
从没在世界的森林里飞翔
fly in no forest in the world.
如果它们生活在野外 我们该称呼它们？
who were they when they lived in the wild?
这些鹦鹉自己还记得吗？
do the birds themselves even remember?
Ryan认为 知识匮乏
for ryan,the lack of knowledge
在其它无数的问题上 雪上加霜
added to countless other problems.
很多鸟类来到这里时 健康状况非常差
most of the birds arrived in extremely poor health
很多鸟类的亲缘关系很近 就像双胞胎一样
and many are as closely related as identical twins.
我们处理了很多斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉的问题
watson: we adopted a lot of problems with the spix's macaws,and this year,
今年我们才真正认识到
what we've really learnt is that they're not
它们不像我们想象的那样 容易配对
as easy to put together as a pair
以及和谐相处
and be compatible as what we initially thought they were.
好的 好孩子
all right,good girl.
小组绘制了每种鸟的基因蓝图
abraham: the team creates a precise map of each bird's dna,
然后把基因最相近的鹦鹉配对
and the macaws are then paired up with their most genetically suitable partners.
嗯?
hmm?
你认为呢?
what do you think?
这个好吗?
is that good here?
噢？你喜欢吗?
yeah? you like it?
好的
good.
基因相近并不一定会产生浪漫
abraham: compatible genes don't always create romance.
运气好的话
but with luck,some of these birds
这些鸟5年后能够历史性地 回到巴西的家乡
could make the historic journey home to brazil in just five years.
如果这种世界上最稀有的鸟类
juniper: if the spix's macaw can come back
斯皮克斯金刚鹦鹉能够回家
from being the world's rarest bird
再次在野外生活
to once more being established in the wild,
我认为这将是一个启示
I think it would be an inspiration
希望的标志 以及我们有能力做一些事情
and a signal of hope and our ability to do things
获得一些成果
that would have ramifications well beyond
意义远胜于挽救天蓝色鹦鹉
the fortunes of that one blue parrot.
这些顽皮的鹦鹉的未来
abraham: the future of the playful parrots
在于这些最后幸存者的成功
hangs on the success of these last captive birds.
对于其他一些动物
with other species,
养殖相对容易
breeding the animals is the easy part.
新生儿来了就麻烦了
it's once they're born that the trouble begins.
在西班牙南部的Dona国家公园
in dona national park,in southern spain,
生物学家穿好实验衣服
a biologist suits up for an encounter
去看一个国家级珍宝
with a national treasure.
非常珍贵
something so precious,
它受到最严格的生物保护
he's protected behind the strictest biosecurity.
它叫ECO
his name is eco,
它是伊比利亚猞猁 有6个星期大了
and he's a six-week old iberian lynx.
ECO是地球上仅存的 少数几个伊比利亚猞猁之一
eco is one of just a handful of iberian lynx cubs on the planet.
它也是双胞胎
he's also a twin,
但他的兄弟被关在隔壁的围栏里
but his brother is kept in a pen next door,
这是有原因的
and for good reason.
如果兄弟俩在一起
if they were put together,
ECO可能会杀死兄弟
eco would probably kill him.
100年前
a century ago,
超过10万只猞猁生活在 西班牙和葡萄牙的灌木丛林
over 100,000 lynxes stalked the scrubland of spain and portugal.
作为夜间活动的肉食动物
nocturnal carnivores,
它们几乎以兔子为食
they feed almost exclusively on rabbits.
20世纪50年代
in the 1950s,
人类引入了一种 叫做多发粘液瘤病的病毒
humans introduced a viral disease called myxomatosis
来控制兔子的数量
to control the rabbit population.
兔子死光后 猞猁挨饿了
as the rabbits disappeared,the lynxes starved.
2007年  商场、公路
by 2007,shopping malls,highways,
和新公寓都占据了 猞猁的栖息地
and new apartments had stolen their land.
现在 只有100多只猞猁
now,just over 100 lynxes are making
在最后栖息地Andalucia生活
their last stand here in andalucia.
[ 鸟歌唱 ]
[ birds singing ]
4年前
four years ago,
Astrid vargas博士及其同事
dr.astrid vargas and her colleagues
开始不断地努力
began a tireless effort
挽救世界上最濒危的猫科动物
to save the world's most endangered cat.
但他们很快发现 这些山猫有一个秘密
but they would soon discover that these cats had a dark secret.
繁殖猞猁
woman: breeding lynxes
通常来说比较容易
in captivity in general should be easy,
同欧亚猞猁
like eurasian lynxes,
以及美洲野猫一样 容易繁殖
bobcats,are easy to breed.
我就想圈养繁殖伊比利亚猞猁也很容易
and I thought it was going to be very easy to breed iberian lynxes in captivity,
但伊比利亚猞猁是复杂的动物
but they are complicated animals.
开始成功地获得三胞胎
abraham: the first success was a set of triplets --
一个雄性和两个雌性猞猁
a male and two females --
分别叫做brezo, brezina和brisa.
brezo,brezina,and brisa.
1个月以来 幼猞猁在一起开心玩耍
for a month,the cubs played happily together
直到 没有任何预兆
until,without warning,
brezo狠毒地杀死了brezina
brezo turned on brezina and viciously killed her.
我们第一次发现这种情况时
vargas: the first time that it happened to us,
它在我们的第一个猞猁窝里
it was with our first litter
发生这样的事情 我们完全没有预料
and we were completely unaware that this could happen
我们对这种残忍的攻击 感到很震惊
and we were shocked about the brutality of the attacks.
更多的幼猞猁表现出 烦扰的行为模式
abraham: more cubs revealed a disturbing pattern.
在第二个月
in their second month,
它们进入“打斗期”
they enter "fighting season."
兄弟姐妹互相搏斗 直到死亡
siblings turn on one another and fight to the death.
我们记录的最早打斗时间是 第37天
vargas: the earliest fight we've ever had was at day 37
就是这个毛茸茸的可爱小猞猁
which is this really lovely fuzzball
看上去完全无害
that looks completely harmless
它会用残忍方式 杀死另外一个幼猞猁
and its capable of killing another cub
例如咬断喉咙
with brutal aggression,like severing the throat.
它们就像着了魔 只想打斗
they become,like,possessed,and they just want to fight.
更糟糕的是 打斗期持续很长时间
and the worst is that it lasts for a very long time.
令人讽刺的是 这个进化策略
abraham: ironically,an evolutionary strategy
强者生存
to ensure that only the strongest survive
突然威胁整个物种的未来
suddenly threatened the future of the entire species.
Vargas博士及其同事
dr.vargas and her crew
建立一个系统
set up a system
24小时监视这些猞猁
to monitor the cats 24 hours a day.
使用遥控摄像机 志愿者可以盯着幼猞猁
remote cameras allow volunteers to keep a watchful eye on the cubs.
打斗发生时 如果猞猁母亲无法阻止
when a fight breaks out,if the mother can't separate them,the researchers have to
研究人员就要扳开猞猁 干涉打斗
brave the claws and step into the fray.
像ECO一样  幼猞猁就是这样分开的
cubs like eco are separated from their siblings
直到打斗期结束
until the fighting period passes.
最后它被重新放进成年猞猁围栏里
eventually,he'll be reintroduced to the adult pens
它在那里学习猞猁之道
where he'll learn what it means to be a lynx.
4年来 中心养殖了24只幼猞猁
in only four years,the center has produced 24 cubs.
到这个水平
at this rate,
研究人员最快到明年 就可以把猞猁放回野外
they could begin returning animals to the wild as soon as next year.
但是Vargas博士警告说
but dr.vargas cautions that without a serious effort
不保护灌木丛林地的话
to protect the mediterranean scrubland,
单单这个繁殖计划
the program on its own
并不能挽救伊比利亚猞猁
is not going to save the iberian lynx.
我认为 其实这个繁殖计划
vargas: I see that the breeding program is actually
只是保护猞猁的一个辅助方式
a support tool for lynx conservation.
我们不能把猞猁关在牢笼里
we don't want them in jail,we want them
我们希望猞猁在野外自由奔跑
out in the wild and free-roaming,
如果西班牙的猞猁灭绝了
so if the lynx were to go extinct in spain,
这是可耻的事情 连西班牙这样的发达国家
it would be a complete shame that a rich country like spain
也不能保护野生动物
could not maintain its wild population.
非常令人难堪
it would be completely embarrassing,
我们也没有权利
and we would have no right
叫其他人来保护野生动物了
to tell anybody about conserving their wildlife,definitely.
我们依靠圈养繁殖
when we depend upon captive breeding
大自然是动物生活的地方 丢下大自然不管的话
and let the environment where the species came from go,
动物就没有地方可去了
so -- well,they don't have a place to go back to.
你不能把动物 例如苏门答腊犀牛
you can't return something like a sumatran rhino
或者伊比利亚鹦鹉 放回旧环境中
or an iberian lynx to just any old environment.
动物真的需要回到
it really needs to be returned to the environment
它们演变了几千年的环境中
that it evolved in over hundreds of thousands of years in many cases.
保护野生动物是 需要政府努力去做的事情
abraham: conserving wildlife is a struggle all governments face,
尤其是中国政府
but nowhere more so than in china,
在中国 世界上最后一个雌性斑鳖
where the world's last female rafetus turtle
将要被带到新家
is about to be introduced to her new home.
旅行了600里 花了17小时
600 miles and 17 hours into the journey,
小组到达苏州公园
the team arrives at the suzhou zoo.
公园专门建造了独立的池塘
the zoo has constructed a divided breeding pond
池塘一边给雌性斑鳖
for the occasion -- one side for the female,
另一边给雄性斑鳖
one for the male.
几天后
in a few days,
如果斑鳖没有攻击行为
if the turtles don't show any aggression,
中间的门会被打开
the gate will be opened.
这里聚集了很多人
crowds have gathered
见证著名的雌性斑鳖的光临
to witness the arrival of the famous female.
今天很特别
davis: this is special because it is
它是中国最大的乌龟
the largest turtle in china,
是中国最后几个斑鳖之一
it is one of the most revered turtles in china,
这是生活在中国的 已知的最后的雄性和雌性斑鳖
and this is the last male and the last female known in china,
所以无论是对我们生物保护学家 还是对中国人民
so it's important not just to us as conservation biologists
这都是很重要的事情
but to the chinese people,
这是非常重要的时刻
this is an extremely important event.
如果你移向一边
man: if you just move aside,
我也跟着移动 明白
we're going to come right by.I understand.
不要放到水里
man: do not put in the water.
放松点
davis: easy.
放松点 放松点
easy,easy,easy,easy.
我抓到它了
I've got her.
走吧
here we go.
好的 把它放在台阶上
all right,set her on the step.
放松点 它走了
easy,baby,easy -- there she goes.
哇！
whoa!
与雌性斑鳖的老家相比
abraham: the new pond is a paradise
新池塘是天堂 它很开心
compared to her old home,and the female is happy
正从板条箱出来
just to be out of the crate.
很好 它来了
excellent.there she is.
第一阶段的成功了 小组成员兴高采烈
team turtle is elated with the success of phase one.
它是地球上同类中 最后一个雌性斑鳖
man: this is the last female on the planet of this species of turtle.
从某种意义上说
and this is literally
这是挽救斑鳖的最后一次机会
the last chance we have to save this species.
第二阶段是诱哄雄性斑鳖
abraham: phase two is to coax the male
要通过池塘中间的围栏来完成
through a connecting tunnel into his half of the pond.
围栏是有原因的
but the fence is there for a reason.
雄性的体型是雌性的三倍
the male is nearly three times the size of the female,
雄性斑鳖已经杀了另外一只龟
and he has already killed another turtle.
他攻击雌性 而不是与雌性交配
instead of mating with her,he could attack her.
如果我们引见它们
davis: if we introduce them
雄性斑鳖没认出雌性斑鳖
and he does not recognize the female as a female,
就会发生打斗
then there will be a fight.
我们担心
we are concerned,
我希望池塘弥漫爱情
but I'm hoping love is in the air,
下午就会知道结果
and I believe we'll know this afternoon
当雄雌看到 护栏另一边的雌性
when we see the male and the female on opposite sides of the protective barrier
它们会相互对望、相互嗅探
able to see each other and smell each other
相互抚摸 双方都是第一次
and touch each other for the first time.
意想不到的雌性气味
abraham: the unexpected scent of a female
引诱雄性斑鳖来到池塘中
lures the male into his half of the pond.
好奇的不止他一个
and he's not the only one whose interest is piqued.
现在两个斑鳖有一夜的时间
now the two will have the night to get acquainted
隔着门互相认识
through the dividing gate.
[ 雷声 ]
[ thunder crashes ]
第二天 苏州下了雷雨
the next day,a rainstorm inundates suzhou,
对两个斑鳖来说
but for the turtles,
天气使心情更愉快
the weather is just setting the mood.
雄性和雌性在护栏两边度过一晚
the male and female have spent the night pacing the fence,
Kuchling博士认为 开门时机已经成熟
and dr.kuchling insists the time is right to open the gate.
雌性斑鳖美极了
kuchling: the female definitely is a very good-looking girl,
我希望雌性斑鳖也认为
and the male,I hope the female
雄性斑鳖也帅呆了
thinks the same of the male,that he is a good-looking guy.
我认为
from what I can tell,
雌性斑鳖明显对隔壁的
she's obviously interested of what's next door
雄性斑鳖感兴趣
and that this is a male.
因此我们认为
this is also one reason why we are confident
现在可以打开门了
that we should open the gate now.
[ 说中文 ]
[ speaking chinese language ]
动物园同意了
abraham: the zoo gives the team the final go-ahead.
重要的引见时刻
it's time for the big introduction.
雄性斑鳖有点犹豫
the male hesitates to approach the open gate
小组时刻准备紧急拆散
and the team gets ready for an emergency separation.
最后
finally,
他游过去了
he makes his move.
他来了
man: there he goes.
他直奔雌性斑鳖
he's headed right towards her.
两只斑鳖消失于碧波中
abraham: and the two disappear into a swirl of bubbles.
池塘中正在发生某些事
there's something going on in the middle of the pond here.
水下求爱开始了
abraham: the underwater courtship begins
小组密切地查看是否有 任何攻击的迹象
as the team closely watches for any signs of aggression.
迄今所有迹象表明 撮合成功
but so far,all signs point to a successful match.
噢 她来了
davis: oh,there she goes!
几个月后
abraham: in a few months,
雌性斑鳖会产下卵
the female will lay her eggs,
那时小组会知道 这个计划是否可行
and they'll know for certain if the plan has worked.
雌性斑鳖能产下20-80个卵
calle: she can lay anywhere from 20 to 80 eggs
只要一两个能受精
and so one or two fertile clutches
地球上斑鳖的数量 就会增加一个数量级
would by an order of magnitude increase the number of this species on earth.
如果计划不成功
if this effort is not successful,
斑鳖就会灭绝
the species will become extinct.
斑鳖的未来就依靠这些
the future of the rafetus turtle now depends upon
危险、有限的基因了
a dangerously limited gene pool.
但生物学家一致同意
but biologists agree,
没有任何借口 让这些动物灭绝
this is no reason to let the animals die out.
有时候 有人说
mittermeier: sometimes people say,
如果某个物种低于一定数量
"if a species gets below a certain number,
从基因上说 该物种就无法维持了
it's no longer viable genetically."
这不可信
I don't believe it.
我认为 只要还有一个能怀孕的雌性
I think that if there's a pregnant female remaining,
你就要努力挽救该物种
you should make the effort to try to bring that species back
防止灭绝
from the brink of extinction.
如此严峻的圈养繁殖
abraham: captive breeding in such extreme cases
能使物种生存下去
can keep a species alive.
到了数量足够多
but by the time the captive population is big enough
能够放回野外的时候
to return to the wild,
问题就会变成
the question will be,
还有野外栖息地吗？
are there any wild places left?
早上 森林充满生机
it's morning,and the forest
一些最难得的进化实验
comes alive with some of evolution's most unusual experiments.
马达加斯加狐猴
sifakas,
环尾冕狐猴
ringtailed and crowned lemurs,
寻找新鲜树叶
set out to forage for fresh leaves.
但这些狐猴的家乡 马达加斯加离这里很远
but these lemurs are a long way from their native madagascar.
它们生活在美国南部
they're living in the southern united states,
杜克大学的狐猴中心
at the duke university lemur center,
狐猴中心繁殖了 来自世界各地的灵长类动物
the largest collection of endangered primates in the world.
虽然狐猴的品种出奇地多
though amazingly diverse,
它们都是一种灵长类祖先的后代
all lemurs are descended from a single primate ancestor
祖先生活中6千万年前的马达加斯加
that colonized madagascar more than 60 million years ago.
从单一的种类
from that one source,
进化成至少70个品种
at least 70 different kinds evolved.
我总认为 狐猴是进化的最佳典范
woman: I mean,I always think of lemurs as being evolution's finest moment.
它们是非常壮观的动物群落
they're just a spectacular array of animals in and of themselves.
漂亮、魅力非凡
they're beautiful,they're charismatic,
小狐猴只有老鼠那么大
they go from a tiny mouse-lemur-sized
而大狐猴比得上大猩猩
all the way up -- at one point,there were giant lemurs that were the size of gorillas.
马达加斯加是世界的第四大岛
abraham: madagascar is the fourth biggest island in the world,
生活的动物超过20万种
and of its 200,000 known species,
3/4的物种无法在世界其他地方找到
ree-fourths are found nowhere else on earth.
但是人类破坏了岛上80%的森林
but humans have cleared the island of over 80% of its forests.
树木消失了
and as the trees have disappeared,
狐猴也跟着灭亡
so too have the lemurs.
近些年来 大规模灭绝不断发生
mittermeier: madagascar is one of the most striking examples
马达加斯加是一个极端的例子
of large-scale extinctions in recent times.
人类大约2千年前来到马达加斯加
people first arrived in madagascar maybe 2,000 years ago.
从那时起
and since that time,
许多令人感兴趣的动物都消亡了
many very interesting creatures have disappeared,
包括8个类属
including eight genera
至少15种大狐猴
and at least 15 species of giant lemurs.
现在 马达加斯加遭遇 全球许多采矿公司掠夺
woman: right now,madagascar is hitting the radar of a lot of mining companies around the world.
但是 对于森林毁坏后
however,there isn't really a plan
动物栖息地的安排
for what's going to happen to the inhabitants
还没有具体的计划
of the forests that are going to be destroyed,
这是事实
and that's -- it's just a fact
森林被毁掉了
that the forest will be destroyed,
狐猴失掉了栖息地
the lemurs will lose their homes.
[ 狐猴呼叫 ]
[ lemurs chattering ]
杜克狐猴中心为狐猴建立了栖息地
abraham: the duke lemur center has created a noah's ark of lemurs,sheltering 200 animals
有200个动物 20个类属
from 20 different species.
有些狐猴 如提图斯狐猴
some,like titus,
是同类中唯一圈养的动物
are the only captive members of their kind.
[ 提图斯狐猴叽喳叫 ]
[ titus gibbers ]
提图斯狐猴是世界上
woman: titus is the only
唯一一种圈养的冕狐猴
golden crowned sifaka in captivity in the world,
野生提图斯狐猴非常少
and his population in the wild is critically endangered.
没有伙伴的灵长类动物
any primate that doesn't have another primate as a friend
是孤独的
I would say is lonely.
一般来说 灵长类是群居动物
I mean,in general,primates are gregarious.
如果他有雌性狐猴
and so I definitely think he'd be happier
他一定会更快乐
if he had a female companion,
但我们尽可能丰富他的生活
but we try to enrich him as much as possible,
他的确乐于现状 还有人类的陪伴
and he does enjoy the presence and company of humans,
我们也一直这么做
so we try and do that as well
使他的生活尽可能舒服
and just kind of make his life as comfortable as possible.
中心的科学家
abraham: scientists at the center
努力圈养繁殖狐猴
are spearheading efforts to breed lemurs in captivity,
通过实验和尝试
uncovering the mysteries of their biology
揭开狐猴的生理谜团
through trial and error.
今天 科学家希望
today,they're hoping for another successful pregnancy
红狐猴Carina再次怀孕成功
with a red-ruffed lemur named carina.
Carina两个月前怀孕
woman: she bred about two months ago.
我们先要做触诊
so we're going to do a palpation,initially,
看看能否触摸到胎儿
to see if we can feel fetuses.
然后再做超声波
and after that we're going to do an ultrasound
确定肚子是否有胎儿
just to verify that if there are fetuses there,
一个 或者两个
one,and then two,
如果胎儿发育了 它们在哪里呢
if they're viable and what their position is.
我们要搜索子宫
and what we're going to do is start looking for the uterus
和可能的胎儿
and possible fetuses,so what I'm going to do
我从这里着手
is come around this way...
好 这里有一个胎儿
okay,so we have a fetus right here,
就在这里
right in that region.
这里是胎儿的脊骨
so this is the spine of the fetus right there.
这里是跳动的心脏
this is actually the beating heart right there.
我想是三胞胎 Nicki
I think you may even have a threesome here,nicki.
三胞胎!
you may have triplets!
振奋人心!
how exciting!
[ 笑声 ]
[ laughter ]
这里是狐猴的安全避难所
yoder: we see ourselves as a safe-haven for lemurs,
最终目标是
with the ultimate goal
一旦环境条件稳定下来
of reintroducing species to madagascar
重新把狐猴放回马达加斯加
once the environmental situation is stabilized.
我们希望狐猴繁殖下去
the hope is that we can keep the species going,
基因不断发育
keep them genetically viable,
通过自由繁殖环境的实验
and by virtue of having the experience of the free-ranging environment
狐猴以前遇到过这些环境
that they are already sort of predisposed
它们就会知道 如何在马达加斯加的森林中生存
to know how to survive in the jungles of madagascar when they get there.
马达加斯加的总统承诺
abraham: madagascar's president has promised to triple
把国家保护区的面积增加至三倍
the country's protected areas,
自然资源保护学家表示乐观
and conservationists are optimistic
至少一些狐猴的栖息地 能够保存下来
that at least some of the lemur's habitat will survive.
也有人争辩说
but others argue
圈养的动物 失去了野生祖先拥有的生存技能
that captive-born animals have lost the survival skills of their wild ancestors.
随着越来越多的物种
with more and more species
降低到少数的圈养数量
reduced to small,captive populations,
很多人怀疑
many wonder
这些动物是否还有 野外生存的未来
if they really have any future in the wild.
科罗拉多北部的平原
on the rolling plains of northern colorado,
一个仓库的科学家获得 极大的科学成就
a warehouse conceals a towering scientific achievement --
一种动物从死亡中复活了
a species resurrected from the dead.
27年前
27 years ago,
黑足貂
the black-footed ferret --
北美唯一的本地貂
the only ferret native to north america --
曾被认为灭绝
was considered extinct.
直到一个叫Shep的农场狗
man: it wasn't until a ranch dog named shep
发现了已知的 最后的黑足貂群
actually found the last known wild population of black-footed ferrets.
狗带回了一只死掉的黑足貂 到农场主的家门前
he brought a dead black-footed ferret to his owner's door.
自然保护界发生了 翻天覆地的反应
it turned the conservation world upside-down.
美国鱼类及野生动物服务部门
abraham: the u.s.fish and wildlife service
派出一支搜寻对 找到少量的黑足貂
sent out a search party and found a small population of ferrets.
18个顽强的幸存者
with 18 of these hardy survivors,
美国发起了圈养繁殖计划
a captive breeding program was launched
目标是把新一代的黑足貂
with the aim of returning a new generation
放回美国平原
to the american plains.
Paul marinari是黑足貂保护中心的领队
paul marinari directs the black-footed ferret
中心位于科罗拉多州和怀俄明州的边界
conservation center on the colorado-wyoming border.
中心的每一只黑足貂
every ferret at the center
都可以追溯到原来的18个幸存者
can trace its lineage to those original 18 animals.
数量非常少
population,
小组必须小心地挑选每一个配对
the team has to carefully orchestrate each pairing,
根据基因蓝图配对
matching up mates based on genetic makeup.
我们要把雄性放到 雌性的笼子里
marinari: what we do is bring the male to the female's cage,
就像野外一样
just like it would be in the wild.
使雌性上前 展示她的脸蛋
get her to come up and show her face.
这种方式 雌性感到毫不奇怪
that way she's not totally surprised.
就像快速约会
it's kind of like fast-track dating.
现在 它们首次约会
right now,they're on the first date.
大概10分钟
hopefully in about ten minutes
它们可能会第二次约会 大概15分钟
they'll be on the second date,and maybe in about 15 minutes,
第三次约会 来个大满贯
they'll be third base,and then grand slam.
中心每年繁殖400个黑足貂
abraham: the center produces up to 400 kits a year.
我们从这里看过去
marinari: so we'll peek in here
这一小窝有5个 生活舒适
on clover,her litter of five,
至于小黑足貂的性别
and determine what sex those kits are.
这个是小男孩
that's a little boy.
这个是小女孩
here's a little girl.
几个月后
abraham: after a few months,
小黑足貂来到户外的营地
the kits are placed in an outdoor boot camp
它们在那里学习各种技能
where they learn the skills they'll need
以适应在大平原的生存
to survive on the open plains.
这是从头开始的计划
marinari: it's kind of like a head-start program
在围栏里呆两个月
where they spend about two months in the pens
以草原狗为食
getting fed live prairie dogs
经历自然的洞穴生活
and experiencing a natural burrow system.
我们发现 黑足貂经过这种训练
we find that the animals that go through preconditioning
与那些没有经历从头开始计划的的黑足貂相比
have a much greater survivorship then those just released
生存机会更大
without any prior head-start program.
1991年以来
abraham: since 1991,
中心在美国和墨西哥的18个地点
over 2,400 ferrets have been released
放生了2400个黑足貂
at 18 different sites throughout the u.s.and mexico.
现在大约有1000个黑足貂生活在野外
today,about 1,000 animals survive in the wild,
20年前 这些地方一个黑足貂也没有
where just two decades ago,there were none.
但Paul警告说 黑足貂面临着疾病问题
but paul warns that the ferrets now face problems with disease
大草原也被开发成农场
and the conversion of the prairies to farmland,
还不能确定黑足貂已经安全
and it's too soon to consider the black-footed ferret safe.
这是成功的计划
marinari: it is considered a successful program,
但是 一转眼的功夫
but it can all be taken away,
这个计划就会被毁掉
you know,in the blink of an eye.
确实很成功
truly successful
这意味着关掉圈养繁殖中心
would mean shutting down the captive-breeding facilities
让黑足貂回到野外
and having the species back in the wild
自生自灭
through self-sustaining populations.
但我们决不能离开树林
but we are by no means out of the woods yet.
黑足貂不确定的放生计划 不能只依靠圈养繁殖
abraham: the black-footed ferret's precarious return depends not only on captive breeding
还要依靠草原生态系统的 所有动植物
but on all of the organisms that make up its prairie ecosystem.
这是地球上的一个小宇宙
it's a microcosm of the planet,
在生态链中 每种动物都相互关联
where every animal is another link in the chain of life.
我们知道某个物种的死亡
wilson: we know that the death of any species is highly likely
会大大地影响其他的物种
to influence other species around it.
当你除掉了一个物种
but then there's the matter of what does it mean
它灭绝了 这才是关键
when you pull a species out,you extinguish it,
你只是在生态系统中除掉了它？
you just eliminate it within the eco-system?
我很大程度上不了解
well,we don't know in most cases.
这会导致灾难性的后果
it could be catastrophic there.
以寂寞乔治为例
abraham: in the case of lonesome george,
乔治同类的死亡
the loss of his species left pinta island
使平塔岛再也没有草食动物
without a large herbivore.
那里过度生长的植物
the vegetation,now overgrown,is pushing native birds
使当地鸟类无法建巢
from their nesting sites.
在印度尼西亚
in indonesia,
森林里没有苏门答腊犀牛
the forests have lost the sumatran rhino
犀牛曾经造就了这里的环境
which once shaped their environment,
其他有机物需要犀牛的水坑繁殖
creating wallows where other organisms thrived
犀牛还能散布植物的种子
and dispersing the seeds of the plants they eat.
中国的江河
china's rivers have lost
失去了主要的乌龟：斑鳖
their dominant turtle,the rafetus,
江河污染严重
but the rivers are so polluted,
物种挣扎生存
everything is struggling to survive.
西班牙失去了顶级食肉动物 伊比利亚猞猁
spain has lost its top predator,the iberian lynx,
海岸低地的食物链 失去了平衡
and the food chain of the coastal mediterranean has tumbled out of balance.
每种动物都挣扎在生存的边缘
each animal,teetering on the edge of existence,
这是对我们生态系统的威胁
is a living thread in our life-support system --
地球
earth.
地球表面是生存之地
wilson: the surface of the earth is a living layer.
洁净的水
the purity of the water,
是食物的基础
the foundation for the food we eat,
清新的空气
to the very air we breathe.
这是我们的世界
that is our world.
我们生活的唯一地方
that's the only world we can live in.
我们需要各种各样的生物 生活在我们周围
we have to have an enormous variety of other organisms around us
使我们的生活成为可能
to make our life possible.
生物学家警告说
abraham: biologists rn tha
这些最后的孤独动物 在脆弱的生物大家庭中
these last,lonely animals are each a tenuous support
每一种动物都有自己的贡献
in a fragile house of cards.
没人知道 我们还能失去多少生物
no one knows how many more we can afford to lose.
我相信 目前我们走的路
juniper: I'm convinced that the road we're on
将通向灾难
will lead us to disaster,
不止是生物
not only for life on the planet,
也是人类的灾难
but also for humankind.
不止关系到 猴子和鹦鹉的灭绝
this isn't just about the extinction
也关系到人类的福利
of monkeys and parrots,this is about human welfare.
保护动物 我满怀希望
vargas: I definitely have hope for conserving species,
虽然我是一个乐观主义者
but even though I'm an optimistic person,
长远来说
in the long run,
我看到一个非常黑暗的未来
I see a pretty black future.
我认为 我们的社会还没认识到
I don't think we as a society are conscious
我们对地球的破坏的严重性
of how aggressive we are being to the planet,
虽然我们逐渐关注
and even though we're more and more aware
气候变化和其他的事情
of climatic change and all these things,
社会却没有变化
I don't see a society change.
我们对灭绝的恐龙着迷
we're so fascinated with the dinosaurs that disappeared
我们花了很多时间研究恐龙
and we spend a lot of time studying them
我们试图重建恐龙模型
and trying to re-create what dinosaurs were all about.
噢 我们还有像恐龙一样的 美好生物
well,we've got wonderful creatures like the dinosaurs
和我们一起生活在地球上
sharing the planet with us.
我们不想失去犀牛
we don't want to lose the rhinos
大象、老虎
or the elephants or the tigers.
如果我们失去这些动物 这肯定是灾难
if we lost them,it would be absolutely tragic.
我们完全有能力
and we have entirely within our power,
只需要很少的钱
for very little money,the ability
就能防止这些动物灭绝
to prevent these animals from going extinct.
我必须重复这句话
I have to repeat the phrase,
有生命就有希望
"where there's life,there's hope,"
我们要时刻努力
and we have to always put the effort
力所能及地保护这些动物
into keeping these things while we still can.
Carina健康地生了三胞胎
辛辛那提动物园有繁殖了两个苏门答腊犀牛
2008年 研究人员发现 寂寞乔治有可能与另外一个亲缘相近的乌龟繁殖
2008年6月 雌性斑鳖产了大约50个受精卵
无一幸存
小组希望 下一年再次尝试
本节目有DVD介质
This nature program is available on dvd
售价19.99美元 不含运费
for $19.99,plus shipping.
订购请拨打...
to order,call...
要了解更多
to learn more about
你所看到的“自然“节目
what you've seen
on this "nature" program,
请登录pbs.org
visit pbs.org.